<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Religious loyalty, or, Old allegiance to the new king a sermon, preached on the eighth of February 1684 ... / by Erasmus Warren ...</title>
            <author>Warren, Erasmus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67688</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W968</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15670</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12158880</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12158880</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55242</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67688)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55242)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 905:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Religious loyalty, or, Old allegiance to the new king a sermon, preached on the eighth of February 1684 ... / by Erasmus Warren ...</title>
                  <author>Warren, Erasmus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Clavell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XXIV, 21 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55242:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Religious LOYALTY, OR OLD ALLEGIANCE TO THE NEW KING.</p>
            <p>A SERMON, Preached On the Eighth of <hi>February</hi> 1684. (It being the Firſt Sunday after our moſt Dread SOVEREIGN <hi>JAMES</hi> the Second His coming to the Crown) in the Pariſh Church of <hi>Worlington</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By ERASMUS WARREN, Rector there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavell,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock,</hi> at the Weſt end of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:55242:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55242:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful Sir <hi>HENRY NORTH,</hi> Baronet.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS for my Preaching this Sermon, there needs no Apology. I hope it was <hi>a word</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Prov. 25.11. <hi>Verbum dictum juxta modos ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os.</hi> Vel <hi>ſuper, ſuis rotis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Fitly</hi> ſpoken: and that's enough not only to excuſe, but alſo to juſtifie the ſpeaking of it.</p>
            <p>If there needs one for Publiſhing it, I have one ready. the whole Nation is now (as it were) upon a <hi>Vie</hi> of Loyalty; and Good Subjects are zealouſly expreſſing their Duties to their MIGHTY SOVEREIGN in all meek acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And my ſending out this Sermon, being but an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt or Inſtance of that nature; here's ſufficient vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the doing of it, though otherwiſe it might have ſeem'd too forward a performance. For thus I act but as a Living <hi>Member</hi> of the <hi>Whole;</hi> and as inclin'd or drawn by true natural ſympathy, into decent compliance with the General tendency.</p>
            <p>Who may not lawfully run with the <hi>Public,</hi> when its Courſe is not onely Regular but Commendable? And when all ſorts are eager to pay their <hi>juſt Tribute,</hi> why may not I alſo tender mine? If it be but a Peny, yet it muſt be current, as having CAESAR's <hi>Image and Superſcription</hi> upon it.</p>
            <p>And then beſides; <hi>Joy</hi> is a volatil and vehement thing; and when 'tis ſtrong and high, is hard to be ſuppreſs'd. So that if amidſt thoſe common Triumphant Joys, which ſwell'd our Hearts, to ſee <hi>our Rightful</hi> PRINCE ſucceeding to <hi>theſe Crowns</hi> (when our laſt GREAT MONARCH laid them down with His Mortality) my ſhare was too big for my Breaſt to contain, and I was fain to give vent to my Exultancy <hi>thus:</hi> none ſurely will turn
<pb facs="tcp:55242:3"/> it upon me as a fault. But in caſe they do, I am willing to bear all the Dint of their Cenſure, for the Redundant Satisfaction I feel in my ſelf, tranſporting me into this LOYAL <hi>Guiltineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Papers I preſume, <hi>Sir,</hi> to put into <hi>your Hands.</hi> But not ſo much as a <hi>Guide,</hi> or fit <hi>Rule</hi> for your <hi>Practice;</hi> as an imperfect <hi>Idea,</hi> or <hi>Copy</hi> of your Virtue. Of that RELIGIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S LOYALTY (a Thing as <hi>noble</hi> as neceſſary) in which you are eminent <hi>according</hi> to, if not <hi>beyond</hi> the <hi>Character</hi> here given of it. I nothing doubt, but for the <hi>Honeſty</hi> of them (which is al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they pretend to) they ſhall be favourably accepted. And the rather, as being a <hi>real</hi> (though too ſlender a) Teſtimony of my Obſervance and Veneration of your <hi>Known Worth.</hi> The deep and lively ſenſe of which, makes me juſtly deſirous of being ever continued, in the Relation of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips moſt humbly devoted Servant</hi> Eraſmus Warren.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55242:3"/>
            <head>Since we worſhip'd GOD laſt in this Place, it hath pleaſed Him to make a Great Change in This Nation; a change of our Prince, our moſt Dread Sovereign. But this is to make no Change in our Duty. We muſt ſerve our NEW KING (whom the mercy of Heaven bleſs and proſper:) with our old and beſt Allegiance. Which that I may (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the Apoſtle directs) <note place="margin">Tit. 3.1.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Remember</hi> you of (as it is now moſt reaſonable to do) I ground my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Diſcourſe, upon that Excellent Period of Scripture, which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs in</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PROV. XXIV. 21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>My Son, fear thou the LORD and the KING; and meddle not with them that are given to change.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HERE are two great things recommended or given in charge to the Sons of Wiſdom, to keep them from joyning in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues of the Seditious: RELIGION and LOYALTY. And in vain do thoſe perſons pretend to either, that do not ſeriouſly ſtudy and act them both.</p>
            <p>To ſay we fear the LORD, when we fear not the KING; is to be cant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Traitors. To ſay we fear the KING, when we fear not the LORD; is to be courtly Atheiſts. But when both theſe meet and concenter in us, and grow up together in fitting meaſures, and to a juſt encreaſe: then the union proves venerable and auſpicious: and does not only ſerve to ſhew our Integrity, but is highly conducive to our greateſt Intereſts. For he that is faithful toward GOD, and the KING; as he has made good progreſs in his work upon Earth, and is far advanced in his way to Heaven; ſo he is in hopeful Circumſtances of finiſhing his Task and his Journey fortunately.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:55242:4"/>
            <p>For theſe two Principal Wheels of Duty, being true in their motions; they will not only help one another on by joint concurrence and recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal aſſiſtance; but moreover ſet moſt of the Inferiour ones a going, and ſo carry us along to our deſired end, with a great deal of eaſe, and peace, and pleaſantneſs.</p>
            <p>The conſequence of which will be this at leaſt. That we ought not to content our ſelves with <hi>One</hi> of theſe, as many in the World ſeem to do (tho in truth they cannot have them ſingly) but muſt ſtrive indefatigably to partake of both. As being well aſſured, that they are no whit uſeful to any good purpoſes, but where they are found in bleſſed conjunction. And therefore <hi>Solomon</hi> who was ſo wiſe as to know this, was alſo ſo faithful as to impart it to us in the words before us. Where, twiſting them together in one Sentence, he makes them an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote againſt a dangerous Infection, which might be taken from a ſort of moſt peſtilent Men.</p>
            <p>The Text conſiſts of a <hi>Precept,</hi> and a <hi>Prohibition:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Precept: <hi>My Son, fear thou the LORD, and the KING.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prohibition: <hi>And meddle not with them that are given to change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Precept, without forcing, flows out into ſeveral Theſes or Poſitions. I touch upon ſuch only as do more particularly relate to LOYATY; they being moſt proper for this juncture.</p>
            <p>The firſt is this:</p>
            <p>LOYALTY and RELIGION <hi>are no incompatible or inconſiſtent things.</hi> A Man may be a good Chriſtian, and at the ſame time a good Subject. The Bible doth never tie us to impoſſibilities; and could not both theſe Fears (if I may call them <hi>two</hi>) be regularly exercis'd or expreſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it would never have laid them thus jointly upon us.</p>
            <p>Let none therefore caſt off duty to their Prince, under pretext or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Devotion to GOD. That's to make Chriſtianity patronize Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; which teaches nothing more plainly, and urges nothing more powerfully, than humble ſubjection. <hi>All the</hi> LORD's <hi>people are holy,</hi> was the old plea to juſtifie Sedition, and to palliate tumultuous and treaſonable inſurrection. But the vanity and frivolouſneſs of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy <hi>then,</hi> aſſures it would be empty and inſignificant <hi>now;</hi> and may well beat Men off from ever reſuming it. Can any be too good, too holy to be Subject? Then never let them ſeek a place in Heaven; for there the beſt and holieſt of all, muſt both <hi>have,</hi> and <hi>own</hi> a Sovereign.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:55242:4"/>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> writing to <hi>Rome,</hi> inſcribes his Epiſtle to the <hi>Saints</hi> there. But notwithſtanding their ſanctity and eminence in Religion, he puts the Yoke of Obedience on every one of their necks: <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject unto the higher powers,</hi> Rom. 13.1. Where he muſt mean the <hi>Civil Powers</hi> too: for he ſpeaks of thoſe <hi>Powers</hi> that did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>bear the Sword:</hi> which to do he knew belonged not to the Powers Eccleſiaſtical. And when the temporal Magiſtrate is thus ſet over <hi>all,</hi> upon what account can any be exempted?</p>
            <p>Where people are placed under lawful Authority, Religion is ſo far from diſcharging them from Duty, that it ties them the cloſer and faſter to it. Nor indeed could it diſſolve or looſen thoſe bonds, whereby we are obliged to rightful Governours (in way of juſt ſubordination and ſervice) without caſting diſparagement upon its glorious Author. For ſhould Religion excuſe us from acting our parts, where GOD ſets us down in ſcenes of Obedience; His Doctrine would plainly interfere with his Providence; and His Worſhip undermine and blow up that Order, which his Wiſdom has eſtabliſh'd, in the Political Frame or Conſtitution of the World. But the fear of this, or any thing like it, would be groundleſs and unreaſonable. For where the hand of the ALMIGHTY brings us under command; the word of his mouth ſtill enjoyns us to obey. The fear of Him, never was an Enemy to the fear of Kings. It never ſtood in oppoſition to it, nor tended to the leaſt diminution of it. No, both may grow up and flouriſh together in the ſame people; in one and the ſame individual perſon. And accordingly we find them here in Connexion. <hi>Fear Thou the</hi> LORD, <hi>and the</hi> KING.</p>
            <p>Whence iſſues a Second Poſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>True</hi> LOYALTY, <hi>and true</hi> RELIGION <hi>are utterly inſeparable.</hi> So far from being inconſiſtent, that they cannot be divided. They dwell not apart, but are always combined and link'd together. Where there is One, there muſt be both; and where they are not Both, there can be neither, to any good effect. As many as fear the LORD as they ſhould, fear the KING: And as many as fear the KING as they ought, fear the LORD. It cannot be otherwiſe, the FEARS we ſpeak of, are ſo coupled and united.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:55242:5"/>
            <p>The Men therefore that are zealous for GOD and his ways, and yet go about to murder the KING; we know their RELIGION: And they who are fierce and high for the KING; and yet at the ſame time, will be licentious and impious toward GOD; we may gueſs at their LOYALTY. RELIGION in the one, is for certain, but vain ſhow without truth: And LOYALTY in the other, we may well ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, is but meer ſhadow, without ſubſtance; and both but artificial and ſhining Formalities. However they may glitter and deceive the Eye, yet let them be brought but to a ſearching Teſt, and they will ſoon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be falſe and counterfeit.</p>
            <p>And this methinks puts a proper Key into our hands, whereby to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock the doors of Treachery, and to open, and diſcover the grounds of Conſpiracies and horrid Treaſons. They ſpring from want of LOYAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY, or fear of the KING. But men fear not the KING, becauſe they fear not the LORD; and ſo they are for lack of RELIGION chiefly. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently therefore is it charged upon Traitors, in their reſpective Arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as the occaſion of their guilt and treaſonable Offences; That they <hi>had not the fear of</hi> GOD <hi>before their eyes.</hi> Nor was it poſſible they ſhould, when they had wickedly thrown off the fear of the KING: Both which are ſo conſolidate and knit together, in an union ſo firm, and cloſe, and compacted, as can never be broken. For they are eternally conjoyn'd in their own Nature, as well as by this irreverſible Command. <hi>Fear thou the</hi> LORD, <hi>and the</hi> KING.</p>
            <p>Whence ariſeth a Third Poſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>True</hi> LOYALTY, <hi>is altogether as Indiſpenſable as true</hi> RELIGION. As little Arbitrary and indifferent as That: To evince as much, it is here rank'd (by divine order) in Parity with it: For the ſame inſpired and unerring Pen, that recorded the firſt part of the Precept, (never to be altered) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Fear the</hi> LORD; enter'd and ratified the latter clauſe alſo (to hold immutable) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>and the</hi> KING. So that we muſt be forced to cancel Canonical Scripture, and to raſe this Text out of the Sacred Volume, and to trample upon the Authority of GOD's moſt infallible and veracious SPIRIT; before we can ſhake off the bond of our Allegiance, or croud it into the number of things Indifferent. Yea, before we can ſlip or relax it in the leaſt, ſo as to make it any whit leſs ſtrong or obligatory upon us, than RELIGION is. The Fear
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55242:5"/> of our Sovereign is no more <hi>ad libitum;</hi> at our Diſcretion, no more to be taken up and laid down at our pleaſure; than the Fear of the LORD of Heaven and Earth. We may as well quit or caſt off <hi>This;</hi> as ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to reſign or reject <hi>That:</hi> For the Command is equal touching both. <hi>Fear thou the</hi> LORD, <hi>and the</hi> KING.</p>
            <p>Whence reſulteth a Fourth Poſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>True</hi> LOYALTY, <hi>is true</hi> RELIGION. Not onely Conſiſtent with it, Inſeparable from it, and every whit as Indiſpenſable as <hi>That:</hi> But a real and conſiderable piece of it ſelf. 'Tis part of that Fear, which we owe to GOD, as the Text intimates. For it does not ſay, <hi>Fear thou the</hi> LORD, <hi>and fear thou the</hi> KING; as if they were two diſtinct Fears: But <hi>fear thou the</hi> LORD, <hi>and the</hi> KING; inſinuating that in good meaſure they are but <hi>one.</hi> Differ they may, and do, in Degree: being plainly ſubordinate as their Objects are: but yet in Quality they are <hi>much</hi> the ſame. Are we to fear the LORD truly and unfeignedly? ſo we muſt the KING. Are we to fear the LORD at all times? ſo we muſt the KING. Are we to fear the LORD for Conſcience ſake? ſo we muſt the KING. Are we to fear the LORD above all things? and becauſe the Divine Law requires it? ſo we muſt the KING above all Men.</p>
            <p>Nor need we wonder at this, that there ſhould be ſo near a Cognation, and ſo true a likeneſs betwixt theſe Fears, as in ſome ſort to make them one and the ſame, when between their Objects there is ſuch an affinity and fair reſemblance. For GOD is but the GREAT KING of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and KINGS HE affirms to be GODS upon Earth. <note place="margin">Pſalm 82.6.</note> 
               <hi>I have ſaid ye are</hi> Gods. Where, as the Communication of His Name to them, denotes them to be partakers of GOD's Power; ſo their participation of His Power, entitles them to a ſuitable proportion of His Fear; and implies <hi>their</hi> fear, to be as it were a Slip or Off-ſhoot of <hi>His;</hi> as their Authority is. Which might well occaſion <hi>Solomon</hi> to adviſe as he did; <hi>Fear thou the</hi> LORD, <hi>and the</hi> KING.</p>
            <p>Whence we have a Fifth, and the laſt Poſition.</p>
            <p>To be LOYAL and RELIGIOUS, is the beſt Wiſdom. Elſe the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of Men, aſſiſted and inſpired by the moſt Wiſe GOD would never have perſuaded to both at once, as he here does: I mean in ſo grave, and ſerious, and powerful a manner. For that he might effectually prevail,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55242:6"/> and win upon us, he puts on all the ſweetneſs and tenderneſs imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. He perſonates the near and moſt endearing Relation, of an affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate indulgent Father to his Son; <hi>My Son, fear thou the</hi> LORD, <hi>and the</hi> KING.</p>
            <p>That to be RELIGIOUS, is WISDOM, we are well aſſured; for the HOLY GHOST hath ſo pronounced it: <hi>And to man he ſaid, Behold, the fear of the</hi> LORD, THAT <hi>is</hi> WISDOM, <hi>Job</hi> 28.28. Yea, the <hi>beſt</hi> Wiſdom it is, or the <hi>nobleſt</hi> part of it. For <hi>the fear of the</hi> LORD, ſays the Pſalmiſt, <hi>is the</hi> BEGINNING <hi>of</hi> WISDOM, <hi>Pſalm</hi> CXI. 10. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>choiceſt,</hi> as well as the <hi>firſt</hi> piece of it. <hi>Caput ſapientia</hi> (according to the Vulgar) the HEAD of Wiſdom. And the Head, we know, is uſually the moſt eminent and excellent part of the body.</p>
            <p>And then to be LOYAL, muſt be great Wiſdom too; becauſe it is a Branch of true RELIGION.</p>
            <p>But then hence it follows (by the rule of contraries) that not only the Irreligious, and moſt rank and profeſſed Atheiſts; but alſo that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyal (though never ſo crafty and ſeemingly GODLY) Traitors, muſt be <hi>ſtark fools.</hi> And ſo indeed they are, or will be in the Event, whether they miſcarry, or proſper in their proceedings. In caſe they miſcarry in their evil Enterpriſes, and fall under juſt and condign puniſhment (which God grant they may always do) the whole World will be ſure then to condemn them, of moſt egregious folly. And truly if they chance to go on and proſper (which, bleſſed be God, they have not done of late) yet they are really not the leſs, but the greater fools for <hi>that;</hi> as to the monſtrous effects and iſſues of their folly, which immediately grow unreaſonable and moſt intolerable. As a raging fire is never the leſs hot, for its diſaſtrous burnings; nor a frentic perſon the leſs mad, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he does the more miſchief; no more are Rebels the leſs, but more grievous fools, for their being proſperous. For then their folly gets up and rides in triumph. We want not Inſtances of this nature; Inſtances of the folly of proſperous Rebels: When inſtead of <hi>ſubmitting to the</hi> KING <hi>for the</hi> LORD's <hi>ſake,</hi> they fought againſt Him for JESUS CHRIST; and inſtead of ſubmitting to him as SUPREME, O black Deed! they threw him down from his Throne, and cut off his Royal and moſt Sacred Head: They gave us amazing proofs, and aſtoniſhing Specimens of the madneſs and folly that attend and actuate a thriving
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55242:6"/> Treaſon. Yet this (as ſad and diſmal as it is) is but the beſt ſide of this folly neither; that which we ſee of it here in this Life. But O how hideous will it appear in the next! when its guilt ſhall be changed into conſummate Puniſhment; and all the Actors and Abettors of it, ſhall be conſign'd to torments without meaſure or end. O what fools, what mad men were we, and ten thouſand times worſe! will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Traitors then cry out; in that we ever ſuffered our diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents to ferment againſt the lawful Government; and our factious thirſt to grow ſo high, as not to be quench'd but with our Prince's bloud.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Aſſertions concerning LOYALTY, couched in the Text. None of which ſhall ever fail while <hi>that</hi> holds good; Let but that foundation ſtand, and the ſuperſtructures we have rais'd upon it, can never fall. The Concluſions drawn from them muſt needs be true, if the Wiſe Man's Premiſes be not miſtaken.</p>
            <p>But therefore perhaps it may be ſcrupled by ſome: Does not <hi>Solomon</hi> ſtrein things too much here, or ſtretch them too far, when he thus joins theſe Fears together, as connatural? Does he not attribute too much to KINGS, while he incorporates LOYALTY, as it were with RELIGION; and makes the fear of <hi>them,</hi> ſeem to be as needful as the Fear of the LORD? We well remember he was a KING himſelf, and ſo might ſpeak as he did upon his own account. He could not but be an Hearty friend to Monarchy, as wearing the glorious Crown of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and ſo might write at this rate out of private ends and oblique reſpects: in favour that is, of his Royal Prerogative; and to ſtrengthen and ſupport his Throne and his Intereſt. And which is alſo as conſiderable, his Wiſdom was nothing inferiour to his Dignity, if it did not exceed it. And he being ſo notable and ſhrewd a Statiſt, his letting fall theſe words, might only be a ſubtle Fetch of his; a politic Artifice, or cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Stratagem, to make the Imperial Crown ſit the ſurer on his Head. That he might the better claim his peoples Obedience on Earth, he would make them believe that his Title to it, was derived from Heaven.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer:</p>
            <p>As <hi>Solomon</hi> was a Man of extraordinary Priviledges; ſo in this he excelled for One, that he was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>inſpir'd by</hi> GOD,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55242:7"/> and a truſty Amanuenſis or Secretary of his Will. And therefore when he ſpake or wrote this Text, he did but the work of his Sacred Office; and what he did, proceeded from Divine impulſe, and direction. The Paragraph before us, contains not ſo much his own private ſence (with deſign to aſſert and maintain his Regalities) as the Eternal Mind, and pure authentic Will of the DEITY, therein proclaim'd aloud to Subjects. The words were regiſtred by <hi>Solomon,</hi> but deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from GOD; and are a truth ſent down directly from Heav'n, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Miſpriſion at all in the Revelation.</p>
            <p>If this will not ſerve to arreſt the Cavil, and to ſilence and ſatisfie the perſons that ſuggeſt it: we need but look a little farther into Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and we ſhall find that it ſpeaks the ſame thing in other places:<note place="margin">Chap. 3. <hi>v.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>They ſhall fear the</hi> LORD, <hi>and</hi> DAVID <hi>their</hi> KING, ſays <hi>Jeremiah:</hi> And if in the mouth <hi>of</hi> two or three witneſſes,<note place="margin">Chap. 30. <hi>v.</hi> 9.</note> every word ſhall be eſtabliſhed; <hi>Solomon</hi>'s is confirm'd by ſufficient Teſtimony: and 'tis evident that RELIGION and LOYALTY go hand in hand, as things nearly ally'd, and of like neceſſity.</p>
            <p>But ſome again (glad of any ſlight evaſion) may be ſit to reply; That the Paſſages cited were <hi>Legal</hi> Directions: That they were given out in the time of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Oeconomy, and ſo reach only to ſuch as were contemporary with <hi>That;</hi> living under the Moſaic State or Polity. Whereas <hi>we</hi> being people of another Diſpenſation, they are forein to <hi>us,</hi> and inſignificant.</p>
            <p>To this I rejoyn:</p>
            <p>The Scriptures alledged, are not only <hi>Legal</hi> Preſcripts or Injunctions, but <hi>Evangelical</hi> Predictions. They not onely ſhew what <hi>was</hi> to be done under the Law; but what is to be done under the Goſpel. And though ſome by DAVID the KING, underſtand the Meſſiah, who was <hi>David</hi>'s Son after the fleſh; yet the expreſſion admits of a wider Interpretation, and the Scriptures quoted are very applicable to temporal Princes, as pointing out Fidelity and Obedience to them, and ranking it in a kind of equality with RELIGION.</p>
            <p>And then farther; LOYALTY or OBEDIENCE, is as peremptorily required of all God's people <hi>now,</hi> as ever it was of the <hi>Jews</hi> heretofore. Yea, it is as vehemently and importunately exacted of them, as RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIGION
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55242:7"/> it ſelf: which ſeems to argue that they are no very different things.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Peter</hi> 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of man, for the</hi> LORD's <hi>ſake; whether it be to the</hi> KING <hi>as Supreme.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, That's the Topic whence St. <hi>Peter</hi> moſt cogently argues; <hi>For the LORD's ſake.</hi> So that how could he have urged the <hi>Beſt</hi> RELIGION more forcibly upon them, than he here does this <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> to the KING? And yet (which is worth obſerving) the KING he ſpeaks of (the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour) had no ſuch clear Hereditary Title to the Authority he held, as our KING hath. For inſtead of aſcending the Throne by deſcent from Anceſtors, and a long unqueſtionable lineal Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion; <hi>Nero</hi> (who is thought by ſome to have reigned at this time) was introduc'd in a<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Illud dementer, quod praeterito Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannico filio, Nero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem privignum hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redem imperii fecit.</hi> Hor. Turſelin. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit. Hiſt. <hi>Lib.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>mad</hi> and irregular way. For <hi>Claudius</hi> brought him in, over his own Son <hi>Britanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi>'s head, who was the right Heir. Yet to this <hi>Nero,</hi> were the Chriſtians to ſubmit: Even thoſe Chriſtians, who juſt before were ſtiled <hi>an holy Nation, a royal Prieſthood, a choſen Generation,</hi> and <hi>a peculiar People;</hi> Yea, they were to ſubmit to him <hi>for the LORD's ſake,</hi> and that <hi>as to the Supreme.</hi> As to One,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> who (in St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s judgment) was above the Soldiery; and above the People; and above the Senate; and ſupereminent to all Mortals, with whom they had to do. And if the Primitive Saints thus yielded <hi>Submiſſion</hi> to this Heathen Ruler, whoſe coming to the Empire was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct; and whoſe Title (ſo far) turned upon a wrong hinge: Who but Men as mad as <hi>Claudius</hi> would refuſe Obedience to our preſent SOVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REIGN, or raiſe the leaſt ſhadow of ſcruple againſt it, whoſe RIGHT to theſe Crowns is ſo undoubted?</p>
            <p>And (which is ſomething more ſtill) Chriſtians are charg'd by the ſame Apoſtle, and that in one and the ſame breath (as well as in the ſame Epiſtle and Chapter) <note place="margin">Verſe 17.</note> 
               <hi>FEAR GOD, and HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R the KING.</hi> Which as it obviates all Pleas that might be drawn from the Goſpel to confront or pervert the Doctrine of LOYALTY; as <hi>Chriſtian Liberty, the having no other KING but JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> or the like. And as it baffles all Arguments, for kicking againſt Government, or endeavouring to ſubvert it, which might be fetch'd from the Prince's being of a different Religion, from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55242:8"/> his being an Atheiſt or an Heretic, a Tyrant or a Perſecutor (while the chief Apoſtle commands the firſt Chriſtians to HONOUR one of the vileſt and cruelleſt of the Ethnic Emperours:) ſo it gives us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand again, that RELIGION and LOYALTY are near akin, and in ſome reſpects very much the ſame thing. And therefore St. <hi>Peter</hi> (we ſee) links them faſt together, and by a very quick and direct Tranſition, paſſeth over coherently, from one to the other.</p>
            <p>And truly when <hi>Solomon</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> (the one the wiſeſt Prince and Preacher in the <hi>Jewiſh;</hi> and the other the Prime Apoſtle in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church) concur thus fully in point of judgment, touching the near affinity betwixt RELIGION and LOYALTY, and the neceſſity of both; why ſhould any queſtion the truth of either? And yet they are not onely fairly agreed in the caſe, but ſo perfect and abſolute is the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent betwixt them; that they ſignifie and declare it, by connecting or tacking both of them together, in almoſt one and the ſame Expreſſion. For, <hi>Fear GOD, and honour the KING;</hi> differs but little from, <hi>Fear thou the LORD, and the KING.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how can FEAR which is a thing ariſing from apprehenſion of Evil, have GOD for its Object, who is the CHIEFEST GOOD? <hi>Fear thou the</hi> LORD.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion is pertinent and anſwered thus: <hi>Fear</hi> in the Text, is not to be taken for a meer natural Paſſion, or according to the Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that Moraliſts give of it: But for an ingenuous, filial, and reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful awe, to be teſtified in the reverential Veneration of the DEITY. If this be too narrow a notion of it yet, and not adequate to the full Latitude of its meaning here, as in likelyhood it is not, (for Fear is a very comprehenſive term, and is commonly in Scripture put for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Syſteme of RELIGION) we muſt then amplifie or inlarge its ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication farther, and think thus concerning it. That it is <hi>a Complex or body of holy Virtues and Duties. Fear thou the</hi> LORD; that is (if we would expreſs it in particulars) Love thou the LORD; Honour thou the LORD; Truſt thou the LORD; Obey thou the LORD. And therefore we find in the Bible, that thoſe Graces or Duties, are the uſual Concomitants (if not Conſtituents) of this excellent <hi>Fear.</hi> Thus, <hi>what does the LORD thy GOD require of thee, but to Fear the</hi> LORD <hi>thy</hi> GOD, <hi>and to</hi> LOVE <hi>Him?</hi> Deut. 10.12. And as Fear is there placed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55242:8"/> with Divine LOVE; ſo ſometimes it is joyn'd with Divine HONOUR: <hi>Where is mine HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R? Where is my FEAR?</hi> Mal. 1.16. Sometimes with Divine Confidence: <hi>Ye that Fear the LORD, TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST in the LORD,</hi> Pſalm 115.11. Sometimes with Divine Obedience. <hi>SER<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E the LORD with Fear.</hi> Pſalm 2.11.</p>
            <p>Now this being the <hi>full ſence of</hi> FEARING the LORD here in the Text; it will be of ſingular uſe to direct us into <hi>genuine</hi> expreſſions of our LOYALTY. For the Fear of the KING, being much the ſame with the Fear of the LORD, though ſubordinate, and inferiour to it, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove was noted: Hence it will follow, that our Fear of <hi>Him,</hi> muſt be a ſet of Principles, and a Conjugation of Duties amological to thoſe that compound or make up the Fear of the LORD. And if we would act it aright, we muſt do it in Correſpondent or ſutable Inſtances; onely with abatements equal or proportionate, to its comparative infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority.</p>
            <p>To ſpeak more plainly, and ſo as all may underſtand.</p>
            <p>As they who Fear the LORD aright, muſt have their Fear conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of and exhibited <hi>in</hi> Affection, and Honour; Confidence, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: So they that fear the KING aright, muſt have their Fear made up of the like Ingredients, and ſignified in the like Expreſſions: onely (as I ſaid) we muſt keep to due meaſures ſtill.</p>
            <p>Yea, as true RELIGION, or the Fear of the LORD, muſt conſiſt of and be manifeſted <hi>in, Heartieſt</hi> Affection; <hi>Higheſt</hi> Honour; <hi>Firmeſt</hi> Confidence; and moſt <hi>Chearful</hi> Obedience: So our true LOYALTY or Fear of the KING, muſt ſymbolize, or partake with it here again, and come up to it in a meet and laudable reſemblance. We muſt Love him <hi>Cordially;</hi> Honour him <hi>Greatly;</hi> Truſt him <hi>Fiducially;</hi> and Obey him <hi>Readily.</hi> Should I not preſs this with earneſtneſs, upon the preſent occaſion, I might well be thought to forget mine own Duty, for not minding you of yours. I ſhall do it therefore as briefly, and yet as ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as I can. He that hath ears to hear let him hear.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If we would Fear the KING aright, <hi>we muſt LOVE him Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially.</hi> The Chriſtian Law doth bind us indiſpenſably to love our Neighbours, and our verieſt Enemies. But muſt it not in reaſon then lay more hold on our Affections in reference to our SOVEREIGN? Though the truth is, there would be little need of any Law in the caſe,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55242:9"/> were we but throughly ſenſible of the great Obligations of Nature and Intereſt. For ſo hath the Wiſe and Mighty GOVERNOUR of the World, ordered the matter betwixt the KING and his People; that they can in no degree ſlight and diſaffect <hi>Him:</hi> but in the ſame degree they muſt be unkind and unnatural to <hi>themſelves.</hi> For as we are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the State, He is Eſſential to our welfare; and that full out as much, as the breath of our Noſtrils is to the life of our Bodies. So we are taught by a great Prophet (and I hope you'l grant he knew very well, and will therefore believe him) <hi>The BREATH OF O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STRILS was taken in their pits,</hi> ſaid <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> of a KING, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.20. And impoſſible it is that there ſhould be any thing of Complement or Flattery in the Phraſe. For it was not only ſpoken by that holy Man, but in the depths of his affliction and pious anguiſh; when he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring a conquered and broken People, and condoling a captivated and undone Prince; Whom <hi>then</hi> to have careſſed or ſooth'd up in the leaſt, with any gay, unbecoming, or undue Titles; would have been unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able vanity on all accounts. I, and groſs and damnable hypocriſie too, conſidering to whom he made his complaints. For GOD and he were now alone (let me ſay) and he poured out his bitter doleful Lamentations, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to none but the ALMIGHTY's Ears. Yet in theſe heavy, mournful, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn circumſtances, where nothing of ſneaking, clawing Courtſhip; nothing of fawning paraſitical Aſſentation, could poſſibly creep in and mingle with it: We ſee what a Character he gives the KING; and ſo what his Relation to his People was. I need not make it out to be true and juſt, foraſmuch as we know it came down from above, and to this very day ſtands upon Record amongſt the Oracles of Heaven.</p>
            <p>For many among us (God in mercy diſabuſe and rectifie their crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Judgments) are meanly and baſely opinion'd of a KING. They deem him no better than a meer ſuperfluity, an overgrown Wen, or mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Excreſcency, rather than the Head of the Body Politic. But O! that theſe Men would keep <hi>Jeremiah</hi>'s Deſcription of a KING in their Eyes; that they would but revolve it in their thoughts, and in their minds but ſeriouſly conſider it. Then I hope they would ſee, and be aſham'd of their impious Errour: I'm ſure they would have cauſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to be ſo. For that holy Man ſpeaking by the MOST HOLY SPIRIT of GOD, faithfully informs them, that their lawful Prince
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55242:9"/> (though wicked and unfortunate as <hi>Zedekiah</hi> was) is no ſpare or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernumerary Piece of the State; no uſeleſs redundance or needleſs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendage, but (as Breath is to Mortals) a vital of the Nation. And if ever we ſhould chance to be depriv'd of KINGS, (which GOD for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid) we are ſure to die for't, if not to Nature yet to Order; even to the beſt ſort of Rule or Government, and the beſt expedient of Happy Society.</p>
            <p>And when our KING is ſo neceſſary to our well-being in the World; can we chuſe but cheriſh dear Affections towards him? Who would not be chary and infinitely tender of their <hi>Breath</hi> and <hi>Life?</hi> Why our KiNG is no leſs in a Political ſenſe: For in that ſenſe we are unable to live or breath without him. Indeed we might be able <hi>Spirare, to breath,</hi> without a KING: But then it muſt be as <hi>Saul</hi> did, <hi>minas &amp; caedas, threatning and ſlaughters</hi> againſt one another: But how ſhould we be able <hi>Reſpirare</hi> to reſt, and <hi>breath</hi> together in peace? much leſs <hi>conſpirare,</hi> reſt and breath together in Amity.</p>
            <p>Let all good Subjects remember this, and they will not fail to act accordingly. As we are bound to Love our KING upon other great and numberleſs accounts, ſo even by the Laws of Nature and Intereſt; in point of affection or kindneſs to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if we would fear the KING aright, <hi>we muſt Honour him greatly.</hi> Which <hi>Honour,</hi> though it be to be exhibited in outward car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, upon all occaſions; yet it muſt ſpring up from an inward value and eſteem.</p>
            <p>And to ſuch as enquire for a RULE of Eſtimate (as willing to know how they muſt riſe in the intrinſic value of our KING, which is the root of external Honour and Deference) a fit one is tendred by the brave Commanders of <hi>David</hi>'s Forces, or by his Soldiers in general, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.3. For when <hi>Abſolom</hi> his Son was up in Arms, and engag'd in open Rebellion againſt him; they would by no means have <hi>David</hi> take the field in perſon. But when he reſolv'd to go forth in the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Expedition, they humbly addreſs'd in diſſuaſion of his Majeſty; <hi>Thou ſhalt not go forth: for — thou art worth ten thouſand of us.</hi> A meet Standard whereby to meaſure out the value of our KING. Of all things in the World, we prize our ſelves moſt, and think we have very good cauſe to do ſo. But if we be ſtamp'd with the impreſs of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55242:10"/> true LOYALTY, we ſhall rate our SOVEREIGN <hi>much</hi> above our ſelves, and reckon (as indeed we rightly may) that He is worth many hundreds and thouſands of us.</p>
            <p>And the ſame Heroes, or others, like them, have left another RULE upon Record, in their exemplary carriage toward the ſame Monarch. For when in a terrible fight between <hi>Iſrael</hi> and the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> he had like to have been ſlain by the Giant <hi>Iſhbibenob;</hi> they ſolemnly ſware that He ſhould go no more out to Battel with them. And their reaſon was, That <hi>Thou quench not the light of Iſrael.</hi> So that they eſteemed their KING as the light that they enjoyed; without which there could have been nothing of Ornament, nothing of ſplendor or delight amongſt them. His violent and untimely end, would have been to them like quenching the Day, or putting out the Sun, or like a total Eclipſe of that moſt Comfortable and glorious Luminary.</p>
            <p>But O inhumane Traitors then! and Monſters, Wicked beyond all Epithets! that once hurled Midnight over three great Nations, and ſhut them all up in black Confuſion. That wretched and ignominious Crew, had none of this eſteem for KINGS I ſpeak of; but were ſunk as low in unworthy contempt of them, as on the contrary they ſhould have riſen in generous Admiration. Let their hateful Degeneracy move us to aſpire; I mean, to that due eſtimation of our SOVEREIGN, of which they were deſtitute: And let us never ceaſe aſpiring till we find we are arriv'd at ſuch noble Heighths as may be equally ſignal with their leud Declenſions.</p>
            <p>The Mark we ſee, is fairly ſet up for us in Scripture, and fly above it we may as far as we can; but we muſt be ſure to take our aim ſo high, as not to come under it; that will be ſhame and diſparagement to us. For if we remember, they were <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Royaliſts, who reach'd this gallant and lofty pitch. But we being Chriſtians, have greater Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges, and ſo ſhould not take up in leſs Attainments.</p>
            <p>And here to ſwell our eſteem or value of our KINGS, into its proper fulneſs and juſt Dimenſions; I ſhall briefly mind you of their <hi>Original,</hi> and their <hi>End;</hi> declaring firſt <hi>Whence,</hi> and then <hi>Why,</hi> they are.</p>
            <p>As for the Riſe or Original of a KING among us, it is from GOD a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. Not at all from his Subjects in any way of Derivation or Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance whatever. Elect him they cannot; Confirm him they need not;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55242:10"/> Depoſe him they may not. His Title is from on high, and his Claim from heaven; and none but he who granted him his <hi>Charter of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance,</hi> can bring his <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> againſt it, that is, the ALMIGHTY. The KING, ſaid<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſtitu.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Clemens</hi> of old, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>is the Ordinance of the LORD.</hi> Inde eſt Imperator, unde homo antequam Imperator, ſaid<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Apolog.</hi> Cap. 30.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian. The Emperour is from HIM from whom he is firſt a man.</hi> Inde poteſtas illi, unde &amp; Spiritus. <hi>Thence is his Power, whence is his Spirit.</hi> So that 'tis as much GOD's act, and as peculiar to HIM, to make EMPEROURS and KINGS, as it is to make Men, and Souls. Right was the Opinion of the Eſſence alſo in this matter, that no Man ever came to be KING, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>without GOD.</hi> And the very Poet could affirm<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aſcre.</hi>
               </note>; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>KINGS are from Jupiter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, which to us is more than all beſide, Scripture ſpeaks the ſame thing, <hi>By me KINGS reign;</hi> ſays the GOD of Wiſdom, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.15. <hi>BY ME,</hi> that is, as the Author or Inſtitutor, as well as the Protector and Upholder of them. And therefore where HE complains that KINGS are <hi>not BY HIM,</hi> Hoſ. 8.4. He diſclaims not the Office or Dignity, but only cenſures the Acquiſition or Adminiſtration thereof; or perhaps finds fault with both at once.</p>
            <p>But it may be here Objected: The citation taken out of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s mouth (as a great many more in the Old Teſtament) touching KINGS, is to be underſtood of the Jewiſh ones only: But that <hi>Other</hi> KINGS are <hi>from</hi> or <hi>by</hi> God, becauſe the KINGS of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were ſo, will not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low from thence by juſt conſequence.</p>
            <p>Know therefore in Anſwer, that there are cleareſt Teſtimonies of the Divine Inſtitution or Origination of KINGS under the GOSPEL like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, I mention but two:</p>
            <p>The firſt from the lips of our Bleſſed SAVIOUR. He told <hi>Pilate,</hi> that he could have no Power againſt HIM, unleſs it were given him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="*" place="margin">S. <hi>John</hi> 19.11.</note> 
               <hi>from above.</hi> Whence it is manifeſt, that the Regalities he had (and ſo that others have) were <hi>from on high,</hi> or <hi>from Heaven.</hi> And therefore our dear LORD ſubmitted to the Governours Authority as competent, even where his bloud and life were concern'd. Nor does it in the leaſt alter the caſe,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55242:11"/> that <hi>Pilate</hi> was no abſolute KING, but Viceroy to <hi>Tiberius.</hi> This ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther makes the more for us; in that it plainiy ſhews, that a Power de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legated from lawful Superiours, is as truly from GOD, as the Primitive one is, from which it is derived. And accordingly <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> told his Judges, that in diſtributing juſtice, they acted <hi>not for Man but for the LORD,</hi> 2 Chron. 19.6.</p>
            <p>The other Evidence is St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s; who declares to the Church * <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 1.</note> in the thirteenth of the <hi>Romans,</hi> that <hi>there is no Power but of GOD.</hi> And what Powers does he there ſpeak of? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 1.</note> Why, they were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Powers</hi> then <hi>in being;</hi> the Emperour of <hi>Rome</hi> and his Deputies. Theſe therefore were of GOD. And how were they of HIM? Why, they were not only tolerated allowed, and approved; <note place="margin">Ib.</note> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ordained</hi> of HIM. And therefore in that Chapter, <note place="margin">4. 6.</note> he makes the Ruler to be not onely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Miniſter,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2.</note> but alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Ordinance of</hi> GOD.</p>
            <p>Yea <hi>Nimrod</hi> Himſelf (who is made an Inſtance of Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and uſually brought in as an argument againſt Monarchy) might yet be <hi>of GOD,</hi> as he was a KING, or a greater Title. For when he began to be <hi>Mighty upon Earth,</hi> that is to erect his Empire, or enlarge it (for who can prove he was the firſt Monarch?) he is ſaid to have done it,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.9.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>before the LORD.</hi> Which however ſome interpret to an ill ſenſe, as if he ſet up his Government <hi>againſt</hi> the LORD, in a way of violence or affront to Heaven; yet it is as capable of a good meaning, and may ſignifie no more than his doing <hi>in the ſight of the LORD,</hi> as with his conſent or approbation. There ſeems to be nothing in the Context, that bars the Expoſition as evil or incongruous, if well conſidered.</p>
            <p>Now granting it to be thus, that KINGS are <hi>of GOD,</hi> and Ordained by Him; and conſequently that the Power which reſts in our KING deſcends directly from the MOST HIGH; the ſame Reaſon and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that teaches and ties us to Honour GOD, muſt lead us to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour our KING likewiſe in his proportion: Who is <hi>Deo ſecundus,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>ad Scap.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>next to GOD,</hi> and <hi>ſolo Deo minor, only leſs than GOD</hi> is, as ſays <hi>Tertullian.</hi> And the ſame great Father thought this very neceſſary for Chriſtians to do, even when the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55242:11"/> was lodg'd in the worſt hands: Yea, with his Pen he openly made profeſſion and acknowledgment of as much, to an Heathen Preſident of <hi>Carthage,</hi> who threatned the Church with bloudy Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Id. ib.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chriſtianus nullius eſt hoſtis, nedum Imperatoris. The Chriſtian is Enemy to none, much leſs to the Emperour: Quem ſciens à Deo ſuo conſtitui, neceſſe eſt ut &amp; ipſum diligat, &amp; reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reatur, &amp; honoret,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Whom he knowing to be ordained of HIS GOD, it is neceſſary that he ſhould both love, and revere, and honour Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this (the Emperour's being veſted with GOD's Auhority) was that (by the way) which kept the firſt Chriſtians in quietneſs, and obedience, when according to the ſame<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Si enim hoſtes extraneos, non tantum vindices occultos agere vellemus, deeſſet nobis vis numero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; copiarum? Plures nimirum Mauri &amp; Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comanni, ipſique Parthi vel quantaecunque unius ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men loci, &amp; ſuorum finium gentes quam totius Orbis? Heſterni ſumus &amp; veſtra omnia imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vimus, urbes, inſulas, caſtella, municipia, conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liabula, caſtra ipſa, tribus, decurias, palatium, ſenatum, forum. Sola vobis relinquimus tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla. Ciſi bello non idonei, non prompti fuiſſemus, etiam impares copiis, qui tam libenter trucida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur? Si non apud iſtam diſciplinam magis oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide liceret quam occidere.</hi> Tertul. Apol. cap. 37. <hi>Civitatem obſceſſam vociferantur: In agris, in caſtellis, in inſulis Chriſtianos: Omnem ſexum, aetatem, conditionem, &amp; dignitatem tranſgredi; ad hoc nomen quaſi detrimento moerent.</hi> Id. Apol. cap. 1.</note> Father) they wanted nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrength nor courage to Rebel. Though ſome unworthily detracting from their Pieties, would bear us in hand, that they were dutiful and patient merely through impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and inability to reſiſt, and to make their part good with the ſecular Power. So<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quod ſi Chriſtiani olim non depoſuerunt Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronem &amp; Diocletianum Apoſtatam, ac Valentem Arrianum &amp; ſimiles; id fuit quia decrant vires temporales Chriſtianis. De Romano Pont. Lib.</hi> 5. cap. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> expreſly affirms, that the reaſon <hi>why the Chriſtians of old did not depoſe</hi> Nero, <hi>and</hi> Diocletian, <hi>and</hi> Julian <hi>the Apoſtate, and</hi> Valens <hi>the</hi> Arrian <hi>and the like, was becauſe they wanted temporal Forces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we ſee from <hi>whence</hi> KINGS are, and by <hi>whom</hi> appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But the Inquiry runs on a little farther yet, and we are next to know <hi>why</hi> they are, or to <hi>what End.</hi> And the End indeed is great and high; noble and excellent; every way honourable and worthy of them. For it is to rule and command part of the World, under GOD, who is abſolute Monarch of the whole.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:55242:12"/>
            <p>As we are capable of Government, ſo our Nature and condition make it<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Omnem naturam quae non eſt ſimplex, ſed cum alio connexa, neceſſe eſt habere aliquem in ſe principatum.</hi> Cicero de Nat. Deorum, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2.</note> neceſſary for us. So neceſſary that impoſſible it is we ſhould be happy without it. Nor do we read of any People that ever were ſo. And the reaſon is clear (as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> gives it) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Anarchy is always accompany'd with Confuſion; and that's fatal not onely to the felicity and welfare, but even to the Communities and lives of Men.</p>
            <p>And though the GOD who created us, could have rul'd us, if he had pleas'd with a more immediate hand, appointing good Spirits for his Viceroys below, and leaving things wholly to their care and manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (who according to their ſeveral Provinces or Juriſdictions, might have ſet up Majeſtic Thrones, and Tribunals, and have conducted Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs in their reſpective Lieutenancies, in rareſt Methods of Polity and Righteouſneſs) and ſo have made the Regiment of this inferiour World Angelic or Theocratical: yet (as being more ſuitable to his wiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and more natural, agreeable, and advantageous to us) He exalted frail Men to be his Repreſentatives on Earth: He hath aſſigned ſuch to preſide over us, as (bating their Preſidency) are exactly like us. And as He did thus to other great purpoſes, ſo undoubtedly to this for one; that they might be the more kind and eaſie to us, and more ready to pity and ſympathize with us, as being throughly acquainted with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane infirmities, from their own Nature and paſſions, which are the ſame with ours.</p>
            <p>And as we ſhare in this commune Privilege, of being ruled by Men; ſo we are further happy in this Nation, in a Government Monarchical, which is highly preferable to any other. And ſo indeed it was repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of old. Famous <hi>Homer</hi> almoſt three thouſand years ago, avouch'd it to be the beſt. For in condemnation or defiance of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Rule of many, he cried out
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>— <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> —</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Il.</hi> 2.</note>
               <hi>Let there be one LORD, one KING.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:55242:12"/>
            <p>And thus we have learnt alſo what the <hi>Deſign</hi> of Heaven is, in giving us a KING: namely, that he may rule us under GOD, and that in an humane and gentle way proper and accommodate to our frame and weakneſs. Whence it is evident, that his advancement above us, is for our Benefit. He is <hi>GOD's Miniſter</hi> (as before:) but then he is ſo, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to us,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>for good,</hi> Rom. 13.4. Which <hi>Plato</hi> conſidering, he pronounced<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>vid Sen. Ep.</hi> 44.</note> 
               <hi>Neminem non ſervum ex Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus, every KING to be a Servant.</hi> He meant in an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable notion and capacity. Juſt as Shepherds are Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to their Flocks, or Fathers to their Families; who at the ſame time have Dominion over them. And therefore a KING is ſaid to be <hi>both,</hi> in reference to his People,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Clem.</hi>
               </note> and that as well in the Sacred, as Prophane writings. <hi>Seneca</hi> alſo would have a KING to reckon, <hi>non Rempublicam ſuam eſſe ſed ſe Reipublicae. Not that the Commonwealth is ſo much His, as He the Commonwealth's:</hi> in regard of his ſuperintending it, and the many and great advantages that He brings it. Yea, Emperour (a Title above that of KING) is but <hi>nomen officii, a Term of Office.</hi> And ſo fairly inſinuates, that as many as are ſignaliz'd with that lofty ſtile, are but Public and illuſtrious Servitors of their Countries; as having the principal Charge, and care, by having the ſupreme command of the people under them.</p>
            <p>But this then lays farther Obligation upon us to honour the KING; as making it neceſſary in point of Gratitude, as well as Duty. In that he is our SOVEREIGN, he is our Patron alſo, and our great Benefactor. And ſo the Honour he may demand, he firſt deſerves; deſerves it, by earning it, or purchaſing of it, and that at a very dear rate too: I mean his Royal care and pains in the Government. May this thought weigh with us, and work effectually upon us. Elſe we Chriſtians, in giving <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due, ſhall come ſhort of Heathens. One of which taught, (and hath left it upon Record) <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neceſſe eſt auctorem hujus boni ut paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem colunt.</hi> Sen. Ep. 73.</note> as a needful Doctrine: that they muſt Honour the KING who is the Author of good to them, as they would honour a Father, that is, <hi>greatly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I paſs to the next Particular:</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:55242:13"/>
            <p>Only as I go, I muſt let fall this Note, not to inform, but excite ſtill; That as one ſpecial way of <hi>Honouring the LORD,</hi> is, <hi>with our ſubſtance,</hi> Prov. 3.9. So one proper expreſſion of Honour to our KING, is granting and paying him Taxes and Subſidies to ſupply his neceſſities, and ſupport his ROYAL Grandeur and magnificence. In confirmation of which, it is memorable of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that he join'd Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute and Cuſtom, with the Fear and Honour due to the KING, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If we would fear the KING aright, <hi>We muſt truſt him fidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially.</hi> And have we not greateſt reaſon ſo to do? Remember, by virtue of his place he is Father of his Country. And which we muſt never forget, he has expos'd Himſelf to danger and death for our ſafeguard. Yea, I may ſay of his MAJESTY, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> of himſelf, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23.</note> that for our ſakes he has been <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in deaths oft.</hi> To which add, that he is moſt illuſtriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcended, from great, renowned, and moſt glorious ANCESTORS, And this GOD Himſelf has made to be a ground of <hi>Truſt</hi> for us, and of rare <hi>Expectancies.</hi> For <hi>bleſſed art thou O Land,</hi> ſays He, <hi>when thy</hi> KING <hi>is</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>THE</hi> SON OF NOBLES <hi>or</hi> WHITE ONES, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.17. So that what may we not with humble Confidence look for, that it is fit a good Prince ſhould do for his Subjects. For thoſe Subjects of His, who as they think, and own, that they are bound in Conſcience to ſerve Him with their lives; ſo I truſt will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be ready at His firſt command, faithfully to perform, what they heartily profeſs.</p>
            <p>You therefore that hear me this day, as you tender your RELIGI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON, be not defective in this piece of LOYALTY. which is a part thereof. TRUST your KING, and truſt Him BOLDLY, as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ingenuous and honeſt Subjects. Baniſh all unreaſonable Doubts; down with all Ill-natur'd Fears; caſt off all unbecoming Jealouſies; and let no vainly diffident ſurmiſes boil up in your hearts, or ſloat in your minds. Our RELIGION and our LAWS; our LIBERTIES and our PROPERTIES, are things moſt Dear and Pretious to us. Believe therefore that he will take due care of them; that he will graciouſly pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize and protect them.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:55242:13"/>
            <p>It was the <hi>Greek</hi> Orator's ſaying of the KING of <hi>Macedon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Demoſt. Olynth.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>I ſhould verily think</hi> Philip <hi>to be formidable and wonderful, if ſo be I could ſee he grew great by juſt proceedings:</hi> Queſtion not but we have a KING who will keep and encreaſe his Grandeur, by his Juſtice: and that at ſuch a Rate as to become a meet Object both of Dread and Admiration. I will venture to ſpeak but one word more. Never fear but he will anſwer or come up to that moſt true Character or Definition of a KING, which the learned Father has rightly drawn up:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Clem. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om.</hi> Lib. 1.</note> HE is A KING, WHO RULES ACCORDING TO LAWS. So none ſhall have cauſe, <hi>Juſt</hi> cauſe to complain, either of the Weight or Crookedneſs of his Scepter.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, If we would fear the KING aright, <hi>we muſt obey him readily.</hi> Kings and Rulers are ſaid in Scripture, to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Powers;</hi> and as they have power to <hi>command</hi> and make Laws: ſo we that are under them muſt execute and fulfill them, with all humble and faithful readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and obſequiouſneſs.</p>
            <p>And here to ſmooth our way to this important Work, I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to remove one grand Impediment, or conſiderable Stumbling-block, which Prejudice or Miſtake is apt to throw before many. I mean, a conceit that <hi>Submiſſion to the penalties of good Laws, is Equivalent to Obedience.</hi> So have I heard ſome ſtifly argue, and I have ſeen their practice correſpond to their reaſonings. For they have made light of violating moſt wholeſom Laws, upon this preſumption; that they could ſalve the violations they wilfully ran upon, by undergoing ſuch puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as thoſe Laws inflicted: which in their Opinion would be tanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to <hi>punctual</hi> obſerving them: But this is a weak and groundleſs imagination; and a fanſie moſt wild and monſtrouſly nonſenſical. To hold th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſuffering Penalties is a proper Supplement, of totally abſent, or deficient Obedience; is as much as to aſſert that cutting down Trees, or ſtubbing them up for Barrenneſs; is the ſame thing with their Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs. There is no ſuch miraculous virtue in theſe ſufferings, as to rectifie Obliquities into Obedience, or to work ſo ſtrange a tranſmuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in them, as to render them <hi>like</hi> it, or equipollent to it. Let none therefore venture to infringe Penal Laws, upon this vain perſuaſion,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55242:14"/> that the ſmart they ſhall endure, be it either in corporal or pecuniary Penalties, may be ſurrogated into the place of real Obedience; and by an adequate vicariouſneſs ſo exactly fill up the room thereof, as to be in any meaſure as good as that. It cannot be ſo for theſe <hi>groſs abſurdities</hi> which thereupon would enſue.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>It would change the uſe and utterly invert the Influence of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties.</hi> They are applied as Sanctions to eſtabliſh thoſe Laws where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they are annexed. And not only ſo, but to <hi>inforce</hi> the direct ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of them. But were ſuffering of Penalties <hi>equal</hi> to Obedience; they would not only fail of <hi>this</hi> uſe or end; but produce an effect clean <hi>contrary</hi> to it. For then inſtead of ratifying and inforcing the reſpective Laws, to which they are appendent; they would <hi>juſtifie</hi> Delinquents in their moſt malitious contempts and violations of the ſame. For let them break theſe Laws as heinouſly as they pleaſe, it is but their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going the appointed puniſhments, and then 'tis all one as if they had never broke them, as if they had faithfully kept them. And ſo Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which are intended for the <hi>defence</hi> and <hi>conſervation</hi> of Laws and Government; would effectually work the <hi>ſubverſion</hi> of both, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king way for diſorders inconſiſtent with either.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Suffering of Penalties cannot poſſibly be equivalent to O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, becauſe <hi>it doth not anſwer the Obligation of the Law, and is by no means fully commenſurate thereunto.</hi> Even ſlight Conſideration will make any Man ſenſible, that penal Laws have a <hi>double</hi> force or virtue in them: The one, <hi>preceptive</hi> or <hi>directive,</hi> which binds to Duty: The other <hi>punitive</hi> and <hi>inflictive,</hi> which ties to Penance, in caſe the Duty impoſed be <hi>wilfully</hi> neglected. Whence it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that they who ſuffer by ſuch Laws, cannot reckon their ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings equivalent to obeying them. Inaſmuch as their ſufferings imply ſuch a failure, as leaves the beſt part of theſe Laws unſatisfied and eluded. For therefore do they fall under their punitive, becauſe they ſlighted their preceptive force. Which we muſt own to be <hi>far</hi> the beſt, as containing the <hi>nobleſt</hi> Obligation, an Obligation to <hi>duty.</hi> To which if they had come up or regularly conformed, they could never have been attaqued by the punitive ſtrength or power thereof. And that Penal Laws do <hi>primarily</hi> and <hi>chiefly</hi> oblige to Obedience, which I juſtly call their nobleſt obligation (and ſo that Penalties affixed to them do onely
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55242:14"/> inforce the Obligation) is clear from hence; in that the <hi>ſame Laws,</hi> were they made to be <hi>not penal,</hi> but purely <hi>imperative;</hi> would ſtill bind the Conſcience as firmly as ever.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Suffering of Penalties cannot be ranked with performing Obedience, becauſe <hi>it anſwers not the ſcope, and fulfils not the deſign of the Law.</hi> The intent of the Law, is to make Men <hi>Cives bonos, good Subjects.</hi> But good Subjects we cannot be, unleſs we obey thoſe good Laws under which we live. But then who can think they are obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, who break wholſom Laws, and are puniſhed for it? Much leſs who can think this is <hi>real</hi> Obedience or equivalent to it?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Suffering Penalties can hold no juſt proportion with Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, or be in any meaſure like it, or comparable to it; becauſe <hi>it does not excuſe before</hi> GOD. A Law is a Law becauſe it is Obligatory. And therefore it is called <hi>Lex</hi> (ſay ſome) <hi>à ligando,</hi> from <hi>binding.</hi> But the <hi>reaſon</hi> why Laws do bind is, becauſe they are made and promulgated by <hi>rightful Ligiſlators,</hi> who have <hi>curam communitatis,</hi> the <hi>charge of the People</hi> over whom they preſide, at leaſt in the work of Legiſlation. But whoever are placed in this capacity of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or making Laws; while they exerciſe that Power, they ſtand in <hi>loco Dei,</hi> in GOD's ſtead, and are to be look'd upon as his Agents. And ſo the wholeſom Laws they enact, do not onely oblige us in reſpect of <hi>men</hi> (as being drawn up by perſons fitly qualified, and that had <hi>plenam condendi poteſtatem,</hi> full power to make them) but moreover in regard of GOD, to whom theſe Lawmakers had a <hi>ſpecial relation.</hi> And conſequently if ſo be we tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs theſe Laws, we do not offend againſt man onely, but GOD; whoſe Providence it was that brought us under theſe Laws, and whoſe word requires us (ſo far as they are juſt and righteous) to keep them. And hence it comes to paſs, that our ſubmitting to Laws in the <hi>punitive</hi> ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects or iſſues of them; cannot make us innocent or ſet us right again in all reſpects. Indeed the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enalties we indure, may diſcharge us as to <hi>men,</hi> and place us out of <hi>their</hi> reach, that they ſhall be able to lay no more hold upon us; but ſtill till unfeigned Repentance comes and wipes it off, our guilt will remain in the ſight of GOD. And therefore ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by penal Laws, which leaves freſh and uncancel'd guilt behind it: can by no means be equal to hearty Obedience, which keeps all guilt from entring upon us. Let none therefore be ruled, let none be influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55242:15"/> by ſo vain a thought, as if the ſufferings we ſpeak of, could abſolve us from the tranſgreſſions for which we ſuffer. 'Tis not onely a vain but an evil thought, that. It will be ſo far from acquitting us, that 'twill onely betray us into more intanglements; while by prompting and animating us on to Diſobedience; in our Purſes or our Bodies it will make us pay dear for the ſins of our Souls; which when we have done, ſhall yet be ſet down, and ſtand in a black account againſt us, ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l true Repentance does wipe them out and aboliſh them.</p>
            <p>But though none upon <hi>this</hi> or any <hi>other</hi> ſhallow or deceitful pretence, may refuſe to obey the King's Laws or Commands, I mean ſo long as they are <hi>good</hi> and allowable: yet here a material Queſtion may be put.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe impious Laws ſhould be made and impos'd, and unrighteous commands ſhould be laid upon us; what muſt we do then? Muſt we go on to obey ſtill? By no means. For to ſuch Laws and Commands, there is no Obedience due; that is, no active Ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dience. Yet in this caſe (mind what I ſay, and while ye live remember it) <hi>there is not the leaſt reſiſtance to be made upon any terms.</hi> No, when we have advanced as far in humble compliance, as with Innocence we can: then unleſs we can quietly withdraw, we muſt ſuffer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly, if that be our Lot. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 2.19.</note> And this St. <hi>Peter</hi> calls <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during griefs,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>for conſcience towards GOD.</hi> Which however it be a ſuffering, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>wrongfully,</hi> or unjuſtly (as he ſays) yet there is very great reaſon for it, and encouragement to it. Foraſmuch as in this ſort of Patience we ſhall but tread in the ſteps of CHRIST, <hi>following</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the example which he left us:</hi> and moreover do a thing that will be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as the Context aſſures us) both <hi>acceptable</hi> to GOD, and <hi>rewardable</hi> by Him, and this, among Men, is known by the Name of <hi>Paſſive Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some would bear us in hand that there can be no ſuch thing as <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Obedience.</hi> They are offended that is, and quarrel with the <hi>Phraſe,</hi> accuſing it of plain contradiction <hi>(in terminis).</hi> And truly perhaps it will not be over eaſie to give clear ſatisfaction to the captious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it. For how can one <hi>obey,</hi> and yet at the ſame time <hi>ſuffer</hi> as <hi>diſobedient?</hi> which the word <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> ſeems to import. But however we need not be ſo critical here, as to engage in a nice and needleſs Logomacy, or ſtrife about the word. Admit there be Sole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55242:15"/> and Incongruity in it, and that the Expreſſion be ſomewhat forc'd and chatechreſtical. Yet ſure it may paſs as well as other vulgar Schemes of ſpeech, which if taken in a Literal or Grammatical ſtrictneſs, would be of every whit as uncouth a ſignificancy. Yea, I nothing doubt but we ſpeak as intelligibly and as good propriety, when we ſay, <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> as the beſt of the Orators do in many of their terms, which becauſe they are figurative are accounted Elegant. Though this is no time, nor place, to make full demonſtration of ſo low an Aſſertion.</p>
            <p>But a little to expedite it from cloudineſs and ambiguity. I will lay down this ſhort, and rude, and hearty Deſcription of <hi>Paſſive Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is a voluntary or choſen ſufferance of Severities, either from the Law, or Supreme Magiſtrate, for our non-compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with crooked or unwarrantable Injunctions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is a ſufferance of Severity.</hi> Otherwiſe why, or how Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A voluntary or choſen ſufferance.</hi> That is, as Miſery is cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen before Sin: or as of two Evils, we <hi>will</hi> and chuſe the leaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Either from the Law, or the Supreme Magiſtrate.</hi> And ſo it is <hi>Obedience.</hi> For therefore it is called by that denomination, becauſe it is a kind of Obedience in one ſenſe. Namely, an obeying the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, in the effects of his Wrath; or the Law, in its penal force or Rigor: For that the <hi>one</hi> could not be obeyed according to his <hi>will,</hi> nor the <hi>other</hi> according to its <hi>Precept</hi> or <hi>Letter.</hi> But unleſs the Law, or chief Magiſtrate, or both of them at once, do direct and impoſe the punitive Severities; we have no reaſon to bear them, becauſe they proceed from an incompetent Power. And ſo indeed the nature of our ſufferings would be quite changed. For though under the ſence of them we could not but be <hi>paſſive;</hi> yet our ſubmitting to them, could not be reckoned <hi>Paſſive Obedience.</hi> For that does imply that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions ſtill come from an hand above us; from an hand that has So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Dominion over us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For our Non-compliance with crooked and vnwarrantable injunctions.</hi> For did we comply, we need not ſuffer. And were not the Injunctions and Ordinances upon us (by reaſon of ſome curvity or other in them) evil or unjuſtifiable; we need not boggle at them or refuſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55242:16"/> them, nor indeed ought we; eſpecially when our recuſancy will expoſe us to miſery. And for theſe Reaſons the ſufferings of Malefactors can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be reputed <hi>Paſſive Obedience.</hi> Becauſe they are <hi>involuntary</hi> and fall not upon them for <hi>Non-compliance</hi> with <hi>evil</hi> Laws, but the <hi>violation</hi> of <hi>good</hi> ones. Which ſtates the difference between <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> and <hi>ſuffering for Diſobedience</hi> making it moſt manifeſt. For in the One, we are Innocent; in the Other Guilty. In the One, we ſmart for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of Sin; in the Other, for the perpetration of it. And ſo in the One, we are culpable and puniſhed as Delinquents; in the Other, cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitous and pityable as Martyrs.</p>
            <p>Now if naughty Laws do urge and pinch us, and offer to drive us upon unlawful things: this alone is the Obedience which we muſt pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe under them, or in reference to them. And the ſame <hi>Paſſive Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> we muſt exerciſe or yield to the Supreme Power, in caſe (that without or againſt the Laws) it ſhould ever be harſh or ſevere againſt us. In ſuch circumſtances there's no reſiſting, unleſs with thoſe known weapons of the Church; <hi>Holy Prayers and Tears.</hi> Never ſay this is hard and heavy; never complain that fleſh and bloud cannot endure it. If we be true Chriſtians and loyal Subjects, we have <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> in us to inable us. And upon thoſe Principles, we ſhall as naturally run this way at our LORD's Command; as others do, or can go the contrary. For then we ſhall be throughly ſenſible that this is our Duty, our neceſſary and indiſpenſable Duty, whatever ſome Pens upon incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent grounds, and by trivial Arguments endeavour to perſuade. For if our lawful Sovereign come againſt us himſelf, or others authoriz'd by his Royal Commiſſion, ſet upon us with violence; there's no encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring them, or making head againſt them. If ſo be we can fly from them we may; but in caſe we cannot, or will not do that, we have no other remedy but Chriſtian Patience; which we are duly to exerciſe, in quiet Submiſſion to their unkind attempts, and a ſweet toleration of their ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gideſt inflictions. For we are Subjects to an <hi>hereditary Imperial Crown.</hi> And if the rightful King who at any time wears it, ſhould ſtrein the Government, and by vehement luxations looſen our Laws, and disjoynt our well-knit and compacted Order; and then (during this juncture) ſhould lay moſt heavy burdens upon us: we muſt ſtand under them couragiouſly (unleſs we can innocently decline them) till Providence
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55242:16"/> is pleas'd to alleviate or remove them; though they be ſo ponderous as to cruſh us to Death. We muſt not then fly in the face of his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or meet his Power with armed oppoſition. We muſt not riſe up againſt the hand that ſtrikes us, much leſs go about to <hi>return</hi> its blows, and offer to repel its force with fury. We muſt not dare to bandy or combine againſt our Prince (be he who or what he will) nor chaſe away the grievances brought upon us (though never ſo irkſome) by acts of hoſtility. But (as I ſaid before) we muſt ſlee for ſhelter, where we can beſt find it; and if none can be had, be content without it. Yea, if the fatal ſtroke it ſelf ſhould approach, we may not draw our Swords to ward it off; but meekly expect it till it falls upon us, and then bear it with equanimity and holy reſolution; as believing it is time for us then to die, when we can live no longer unleſs we rebel.</p>
            <p>But is not this Doctrine, or would not the practice of it, be point blank againſt the <hi>Law of Nature?</hi> By no means. In this caſe we are ſo far from deviating from that Law, or going againſt it; that we act in a ſmooth compliance with it, and in a direct and proper Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to it. For by the Law of Nature, we not onely <hi>may,</hi> but ſometimes <hi>muſt</hi> chuſe to ſuffer a <hi>leſs</hi> evil to preſerve us from a <hi>greater,</hi> eſpecially when 'tis the <hi>beſt</hi> and <hi>onely</hi> means left us, to effect that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. Now divine Revelation having well aſſured us, that there is another life to ſucceed this, infinitely better than this is; and that he who ſaveth his preſent life upon ſinful terms, ſhall loſe the future hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier one above: we may without any breach of the Law of Nature, yea with real and laudable conformity to it, part with <hi>this</hi> Life, rather than keep it by Sin, and forfeit <hi>that.</hi> Juſt as a Man may cut off his finger to ſave his Arm, or cut off his Arm to ſave his Body: ſo we may lay down this temporal, to prevent the loſs of Eternal Life. And yet all the while (acting as Chriſtians, upon the ſure Principles of revealed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) we ſhall do nothing repugnant to the Law of Nature; nothing but what is conſiſtent with it, and indeed enjoyned and required by it.</p>
            <p>To ſuffer Death, I confeſs, is grievous and againſt Mans nature; but then to ſuffer Damnation, is more intolerable and contranatural ſtill. Yet we know how the caſe is ſtated from Heaven: That if we <hi>reſiſt</hi> the lawful <hi>Power</hi> (upon any account) though to ſave our Life, we ſhall <hi>receive Damnation.</hi> If therefore we be reduced to this miſerable ſtrait,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55242:17"/> that we muſt either die, or elſe ſave our life by a ſinful reſiſtance, which will infallibly expoſe us to endleſs Damnation; we muſt ſubmit to Death, that we may keep our ſelves clear from that damnable guilt. And ſo far ſhall we be from offering violence to the Law of Nature by our doing thus; that there is no other way to fulfil that Law, in the ſuppoſed Circumſtances, but by this procedure. Which however ſneaking and puſillanimous it may ſeem with Men (who often view things by halves, and on the wrong ſide) will yet be brave and generous in the Eyes of Angels; gallant and Heroic in the ſight of GOD. And though it may a little prejudice the Body, and haſten the diminution of our preſent Being, by a ſhort anticipation of our inevitable change; it will be greatly beneficial to the Soul immediately, and perfective (in conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with other Virtues) of our whole Nature, at laſt.</p>
            <p>That for the <hi>Precept</hi> in the Text.</p>
            <p>A very ſhort glance upon the <hi>Prohibition,</hi> ſhall conclude my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. <hi>Meddle not with them that are given to change.</hi> Whatever it is that they would alter, in way of <hi>Treaſon</hi> or <hi>Rebellion,</hi> meddle not with them; not with any of them; in any manner, or in any <hi>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi> Be not of their number; come not in their<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ne commiſceare.</hi>
               </note> conſults; do not abet them, do not encourage them; do not countenance them; do not conceal them. They are wicked perſons: they neither fear GOD nor the KING (as the Text intimates,) their Sin is<note n="†" place="margin">Read the 3d. part of the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily</hi> againſt <hi>wilful Rebellion.</hi>
               </note> great, and their puniſhment ſhall be grievous. They are no other but eldeſt Sons of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> and ſo a double portion of their Fathers plagues they ſhall inherit. Some that are faſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep in Sin, may dream ſuch wretches ſhall eſcape with impunity: but <hi>any</hi> Delinquents ſhall ſooner be conniv'd at and ſpar'd than <hi>theſe.</hi> Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors fly high, and therefore their fall muſt needs be heavy. They would not onely ſhake the frame of Order; but blow it quite up and break it all to pieces. They deſign not onely to ſhatter the boughs, and to beat down the fruits; but to lop off the arms, and dig up the roots of the Tree of Government. In one word, they ſtrike at the Thrones and Lives of Princes, and ſo they aſſault the Majeſty of GOD: And can we think that Heaven will put up this? No, no? Juſtice will purſue them, and Vengeance will overtake them, and pour down ſuch
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55242:17"/> Penalties on their prodigious Crimes, and ſhall be every way anſwerable to their rank Malignity.</p>
            <p>Remember <hi>Korah;</hi> he was a Peer or potent Man in <hi>Iſrael</hi> (Couſin-german to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi>) but was or would have been one of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Rebel <hi>changers</hi> in my Text: and what became of him? Why, the Earth clave in ſunder and ſwallowed him up alive; and he was never ſeen above ground ſince.</p>
            <p>Or if a Goſpel-example will be more affecting, caſt your Eyes upon <hi>Judas.</hi> He was the beſt Traitor for us, that ever lived. His cruel fact was kindneſs to Men, and his perfidiouſneſs turn'd to univerſal Benefit. But what was the reward of his officious Treachery? Why, He was made to puniſh the Treaſon he committed; and as if no hands elſe had been bad enough for the work, was given up to become his own Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner.</p>
            <p>But put caſe, the evil Men I ſpeak of, ſhould be ſo good natur'd as to ſpare their own lives. And ſay the patient ground ſhould be able to bear them, and they ſhould not ſink down into the hideous mouth of the yawning Earth. Yet may not the Ax or the Halter meet them? Or if they can get out of the reach of the Law; muſt they not die ſoon, and be plung'd into the Abyſs of eternal puniſhment? That's ten thouſand times more than all we can ſay or think beſides. Yet ſo it is recorded touching one of thoſe unhappy Creatures now mention'd, that when he died, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 1.25.</note> he went <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to his <hi>own place.</hi> And where ſhould the Son of perdition have property, unleſs in Hell? And of the other we have account, that when he took his leave of this preſent World, and drop'd a living morſel into the frightful jaws of the gaping ground; he went down <hi>vivus in infernum, quick into Hell.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.33.</note> A ſad Story to be told of any: but nothing more true of all Rebellious impenitent Changers.</p>
            <p>And yet I have one higher Inſtance ſtill, of the formidable portion of ſuch lewdly inſolent and preſumptuous Offenders. Angels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were undone by the Evil we now treat of, and that wholly and finally without Recovery. They tumbled into Hell, and that even out of Heaven it ſelf, by being giv'n to change. Thoſe <hi>Morning Stars,</hi> which once ſhin'd above in happieſt ſplendors, being incruſted with the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55242:18"/> worſt of ſinful <hi>Maculaes,</hi> that of proud aſpiring Treaſon; were inſtantly <hi>abſorpt:</hi> and having loſt their priſtin ſtrength and luſtre, are now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, in St. <hi>Jude</hi>'s phraſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Planets,</hi> or <hi>wandring ſtars.</hi> Which like a company of loſt and forlorn things, deſolately rove and ſtraggle up and down, in theſe wild and black inferiour Regions, never more to fix their woful Errantry. Nor do they onely haunt more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary ſpaces, and like poor forſaken dejected Beings, wander through the wide and melancholy Deſerts of this ſublunary World; where perhaps no other Creatures ever come (all which ranging Liberty of theirs, is worſt Confinement:) but moreover are rack'd with inceſſant fears, and torn with anguiſh of incurable Deſpair; and excruciated with bitter pangs and uneaſineſſes, in all their ſubterraneous or aereal ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blings.</p>
            <p>This, and much more, is ſignified to the Church, where S. <hi>Peter</hi> gives notice that GOD <hi>ſpared not the Angels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 2.4.</note> but caſt them down to Hell, for <hi>rebelling,</hi> that is, againſt him their SOVEREIGN.</p>
            <p>Thus it is evident, That neither <hi>Jew,</hi> nor <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> nor the <hi>Angels</hi> in Heaven, could avoid that Venegeance which is due to Treaſon. From the ſeverity of its Puniſhment, let us learn the greatneſs and danger of the Sin: and ſo not <hi>meddle with them that</hi> (in way of Sedition) <hi>are given to change.</hi> And that we may not, let us <hi>Fear the King;</hi> and in order to that, let us <hi>Fear the</hi> LORD. To whom be all Fear, and Love, and Honour, World without End. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
